<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise of altars, altar-furniture, altar-cringing, and musick of all the quire, singing-men and choristers, when the holy Communion was administered in the cathedrall church of Durham by prebendaries and petty-canons, in glorious copes embroidered with images, 1629 / written at the same time by Peter Smart ...</title>
            <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20243</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11769562</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11769562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60395)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 548:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise of altars, altar-furniture, altar-cringing, and musick of all the quire, singing-men and choristers, when the holy Communion was administered in the cathedrall church of Durham by prebendaries and petty-canons, in glorious copes embroidered with images, 1629 / written at the same time by Peter Smart ...</title>
                  <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction or original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Durham Cathedral --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:48826:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48826:1"/>
            <head>A ſhort Treatiſe of Altars, Altar-furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Altar-cringing, and Muſick of all the Quire, Singing-men and Choriſters, when the holy Communion was adminiſtred in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> by Prebendaries and Petty-Canons, in glorious Copes embroidered with Images. 1629.</head>
            <head type="sub">Written at the ſame time by <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> ſenior-Prebendarie of the ſaid Church, a little before he was expeld, deprived, degraded and impriſoned for the ſpace of twelve yeares, till the ſecond yeare of this preſent Parliament, by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Commiſsioners of Durham, London and York, for preaching againſt ſuperſtitious vanities, and oppoſing then,<note place="margin">Thus, by the meanes of B. Neal and his Chaplains Altars and Images, &amp;c. were brought in. Then, after the death of B. Iames, in May. 1617. There, in the Cathedrall Church of Dutham, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they ſpread over all England.</note> and alwayes before, their unlawfull innovations, brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Durham Cathedrall, by B. <hi>Neal</hi> and his Chaplains, after the death of B. <hi>James,</hi> who died in May. 1617.</head>
            <p>THus and then, and there began the ſetting up of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and Images, with a multitude of ſuperſtitious Ceremonies, changing of ſervices, and corruptions of Sacraments: which beginning in Durham, have ſince that time ſpread themſelves over all the Cathedrall, Collegiate Churches, and Colledges in this Realme; yea and many pariſh Churches have ſet up Altars, Images, and Organs, where they were never before ſince the reigne of K. <hi>Philip</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:48826:2"/> and Q. <hi>Mary;</hi> of all ſuch alterations, and Popiſh Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in our Church, Biſhop <hi>Neale</hi> laid the foundation; who being an old Courtier, ambitious, violent and cruell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that gainſaid him, and oppoſed his doings: and diſpairing to climbe to high preferment by learning and Preaching, (which he could not abide) hee ſet his minde wholly upon advancing Cathedrall pomp, and glorious Ceremonies, eaſier a great deale to be performed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by an ignorant ideot, who hath onely the outſide of a man, then the making of Sermons, or writing books, ſo that in few yeares he got the government of many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals: firſt, Weſtminſter, which once was a Biſhoprick, and yet hath Epiſcopall juriſdiction: ſecondly, Rocheſter, thirdly, Coventry and Lichfield: fourthly, Lincolne: fifthly, Durham: ſixtly, Wincheſter: ſeventhly, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick of Yorke. Thus ſate Doctor <hi>Richard Neal</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 7. hils, 7. Seas, he Lorded it upon 7. thrones above thirty yeares, in the laſt twenty of which he preached not three Sermons, which is the principall office of a Biſhop, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth: Yet at the cenſure of Doct. <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> he ſaid openly, that he was made Biſhop by our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and conſecrated by the Holy Ghoſt: unto what office? and what to doe? to hinder Preaching? to perſecute Orthodoxe and painfull Preachers? to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, cheriſh, and maintaine ſchiſmaticall, hereticall, and traiterous Arminians and Papiſts, <hi>Coſin, Linſell, Burgoin, Duncan,</hi> &amp;c. to heape livings and Church dignities upon his creatures, and favourites, idle loiterers, unſatiable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants, ſeven or eight a peece, above all meane and meaſure: for what good of the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth did our Lord Jeſus make him Biſhop, and the holy Ghoſt conſecrate him? to weare a Rochet? to ſet out
<pb facs="tcp:48826:2"/> Ceremonies? to defile the Church of God with Altars and Images? to gather riches by oppreſſion of his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and to play the ravenous Wolfe, in devouring ſo many thouſand flocks which he tooke upon him to feed in ſeven Biſhopricks, the hundred part of which he never ſaw, nor one of a thouſand ever heard the voice of their Lordly ſhepheard, their Biſhop, their ghoſtly Father, and the Paſtor of their ſoules, as he would be taken to be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſen to the office of a Biſhop by Chriſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by the holy Ghoſt. I have knowne this man about ſixty yeares, (for we were ſchoole-fellowes in Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) when he was plaine <hi>Richard Neal,</hi> and I <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> under Deane <hi>Goodman,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Grant;</hi> hee was then counted an heavy-headed lubber, put out of that ſchoole for a dunce, and a droane, as himſelfe confeſſed at his laſt Viſitation in Durham, 1627. ſaying openly in the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of many, that the three laſt yeeres when he was a Grammar ſcholar of Weſtminſter, he made no exerciſe at all, whereupon it came to paſſe, ſaid he, that when I went from Weſtminſter to Cambridge, I could not ſo much as write true Orthography (put letters and ſyllables rightly together in Latin) and I cannot do it yet: What? not make true Latin, being a Doctor 60. yeares old, when he had paſſed through five Biſhopricks, and was to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to Wincheſter, and Yorke, the two greateſt in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,<note place="margin">This Biſhop (ſaid M. Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in the Parl. 1628.) though he hath leapt thorow many Biſhoprtcks, yet he hath left Popery behind him.</note> after Canterbury. But, howſoever he was an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and unlearned Grammarian, he profited better in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, he had learning enough to run through 7. prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſeven Biſhopricks, containing the one half of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in all which, his principall care and ſtudy was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich himſelf, and his kindred, Chaplains, creatures, and favourites, which he made non-Reſidents, and Tot-quots, heaping upon them all manner of preferments, benefices
<pb facs="tcp:48826:3"/> and Q. <hi>Mary;</hi> of all ſuch alterations, and Popiſh Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in our Church, Biſhop <hi>Neale</hi> laid the foundation; who being an old Courtier, ambitious, violent and cruell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that gainſaid him, and oppoſed his doings: and diſpairing to climbe to high preferment by learning and Preaching, (which he could not abide) hee ſet his minde wholly upon advancing Cathedrall pomp, and glorious Ceremonies, eaſier a great deale to be performed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by an ignorant ideot, who hath onely the outſide of a man, then the making of Sermons, or writing books, ſo that in few yeares he got the government of many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals: firſt, Weſtminſter, which once was a Biſhoprick, and yet hath Epiſcopall juriſdiction: ſecondly, Rocheſter, thirdly, Coventry and Lichfield: fourthly, Lincolne: fifthly, Durham: ſixtly, Wincheſter: ſeventhly, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick of Yorke. Thus ſate Doctor <hi>Richard Neal</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 7. hils, 7. Seas, he Lorded it upon 7. thrones above thirty yeares, in the laſt twenty of which he preached not three Sermons, which is the principall office of a Biſhop, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth: Yet at the cenſure of Doct. <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> he ſaid openly, that he was made Biſhop by our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and conſecrated by the Holy Ghoſt: unto what office? and what to doe? to hinder Preaching? to perſecute Orthodoxe and painfull Preachers? to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, cheriſh, and maintaine ſchiſmaticall, hereticall, and traiterous Arminians and Papiſts, <hi>Coſin, Linſell, Burgoin, Duncan,</hi> &amp;c. to heape livings and Church dignities upon his creatures, and favourites, idle loiterers, unſatiable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants, ſeven or eight a peece, above all meane and meaſure: for what good of the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth did our Lord Jeſus make him Biſhop, and the holy Ghoſt conſecrate him? to weare a Rochet? to ſet out
<pb facs="tcp:48826:3"/> Ceremonies? to defile the Church of God with Altars and Images? to gather riches by oppreſſion of his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and to play the ravenous Wolfe, in devouring ſo many thouſand flocks which he tooke upon him to feed in ſeven Biſhopricks, the hundred part of which he never ſaw, nor one of a thouſand ever heard the voice of their Lordly ſhepheard, their Biſhop, their ghoſtly Father, and the Paſtor of their ſoules, as he would be taken to be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſen to the office of a Biſhop by Chriſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by the holy Ghoſt. I have knowne this man about ſixty yeares, (for we were ſchoole-fellowes in Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) when he was plaine <hi>Richard Neal,</hi> and I <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> under Deane <hi>Goodman,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Grant;</hi> hee was then counted an heavy-headed lubber, put out of that ſchoole for a dunce, and a droane, as himſelfe confeſſed at his laſt Viſitation in Durham, 1627. ſaying openly in the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of many, that the three laſt yeeres when he was a Grammar ſcholar of Weſtminſter, he made no exerciſe at all, whereupon it came to paſſe, ſaid he, that when I went from Weſtminſter to Cambridge, I could not ſo much as write true Orthography (put letters and ſyllables rightly together in Latin) and I cannot do it yet: What? not make true Latin, being a Doctor 60. yeares old, when he had paſſed through five Biſhopricks, and was to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to Wincheſter, and Yorke, the two greateſt in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,<note place="margin">This Biſhop (ſaid M. Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in the Parl. 1628.) though he hath leapt thorow many Biſhopricks, yet he hath left Popery behind him.</note> after Canterbury. But, howſoever he was an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and unlearned Grammarian, he profited better in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, he had learning enough to run through 7. prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſeven Biſhopricks, containing the one half of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in all which, his principall care and ſtudy was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich himſelf, and his kindred, Chaplains, creatures, and favourites, which he made non-Reſidents, and Tot-quots, heaping upon them all manner of preferments, benefices
<pb facs="tcp:48826:4"/> and dignities, to the intent they might flaunt it out brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and aſſiſt him their Lord and Maſter couragiouſly, in ſetting up Altars, Images, Organs, Copes, Candleſticks, and all manner of Maſſing furniture, eſpecially in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting painfull Preachers, under the name of Puritans, though more conformable then themſelves, and in hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Preachers from confuting Popiſh opinions, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian doctrines, concerning Altars and Images, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperſtitious trinkets, with which he peſtered the Church of Durham, and many other places where he had authority, as remaines upon Record in the Parliament, 1628. and printed lately, 1641. In the 45. page thus wee<note place="margin">The Kings Chaplaine and Prebend of Wincheſt. Pag. 45.</note> reade, Doctor <hi>More</hi> called in to the houſe of Commons, ſaith, he was referred to the Biſhop of Wincheſter (Doct. <hi>Neal</hi>) to be cenſured for a Sermon preached by him: The Biſhop he had heard him preach and deliver many paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt Papiſts, which pleaſed King <hi>Iames,</hi> but he muſt not do ſo now: this and more Doctor <hi>More</hi> himſelfe told me, before Doct. <hi>Sibs:</hi> Againe, the Biſhop ſaid to him, you have a brother that preacheth againſt bowing at the holy name of Jeſus, and of bowing to the high Altar: and that the Communion Table ſtood as in Ale-houſes, but he<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 45.</note> would have them ſet as high Altars: This Doct. <hi>More</hi> delivered in writing to the Parliament: And in pag. 33. we reade, that Sir <hi>Dudley North</hi> informed the Houſe, how the ſaid Biſhop <hi>Neale</hi> told Doct. <hi>More,</hi> that hee had often heard him preach againſt Popery (which he ſaid was well<note place="margin">The Prince was then in, Spain. D. Marſhall relat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d as much ſaid to him by the Biſhop of Wincheſter. pag. 40.</note> liked of then) but now you muſt not doe ſo, whereupon the Doctor ſaid, that if occaſion did ſerve, he would not ſpare to do the like now, to whom the Biſhop further repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the times were not the ſame, &amp; therfore you muſt not.</p>
            <p>Whereupon Sir <hi>Rob. Philips</hi> ſaid, By this you may gueſſe, that this Biſhop had a hand in ſetting up thoſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies
<pb facs="tcp:48826:4"/> in Durham, and that he beares good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, labouring to make Durham and Wincheſter Synonimaes: This reflects upon his Majeſty, ſaid he, as if the King ſhould not be pleaſed, that men in their Sermons ſhould refell Popery, pag. 33.</p>
            <p>The like D. <hi>More</hi> told me of Biſhop <hi>Neals</hi> Chaplin, D.<note place="margin">D. Beard ſaid that D. Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſterpreach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed flat Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery at Paule Croſſe The Biſhop of Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him as he was his Dioceſan, that he ſhould preach nothing to the contrary. pag. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Duncan</hi> now Prebendary of Durham, how inſolently he ſhooke him up, being an ancient Doctor, and Prebendary of Wincheſter, about an high Altar to be ſet up there, and to be bowed unto, as in Durham. But concerning Biſhop <hi>Neals</hi> protection of his Chaplin <hi>Cozens</hi> when he was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of high treaſon, for denying the Kings Supremacy, and giving as much authority to the fellow that rubs his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes heeles, as to his Majeſty: you ſhall have more out of the Diurnal of the ſaid Parliament, 1628. when that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the impeachment, and the proofe thereof ſhal be examined in its order and place. To conclude, that which Biſhop <hi>Neale</hi> could not doe in his owne perſon, his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains and favourites of the Arminian faction, did in other places: D. <hi>Laud</hi> B. of S. <hi>Davids,</hi> B. of Bath and Wels, B. of London, and Archbiſhop of Canterbury, D. <hi>Linſell</hi> Dean of Lichfield, B. of Peterborough, and B. of Hereford, D. <hi>Corbet</hi> B. of Oxford, and B. of Norwich, beſides his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, B. <hi>Wren,</hi> B. <hi>Mountague, B. Howſon, B. Goodman, B. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring, B. White, B. Field, B. Wright,</hi> and <hi>B. Harſnet</hi> who made this Epitaph of himſelfe,</p>
            <list>
               <head>Samuel Harſnet</head>
               <item>Epiſcopus Ciceſtrenſis Indignus.</item>
               <item>Epiſcopus Norwicenſis Indignior.</item>
               <item>Archiepiſ. Eboracenſis Indigniſsimus.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Moſt true, he Lorded it ſo long til he ſhould have come to Grace, but the longer he lived he decreaſed in grace, he deſcended from bad to worſe, from worſe, to worſt, as he aſcended from high to higher, from higher to higheſt, even
<pb facs="tcp:48826:5"/> the titular grace of a moſt unworthy Archbiſhop. Al theſe Biſhops were zealous maintainers of Altars, and Images, and other ſuperſtitious ceremonies, depending upon Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, ſo that <hi>B. Neal</hi> and <hi>B. Laud</hi> with their factious aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, and creatures, have beene <hi>Noſtri fundi calamitas,</hi> the ruine, the calamity and miſery of the noble Church of England, which they have peſtered with Ceremonies, and corrupted with unlawful Innovations, wherewith they have hindred edification, and inſtruction of the people by preaching, ſo that for the moſt part they are as ignorant, as ever they were in the blinde times of Popery. they are as ignorant in the grounds of Religion, and as unable to render an account of their ſaith, as they were when all the Service was in Latin before the firſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in the reign of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt. And how can it otherwiſe be in thoſe places where Liturgies are onely read by unlearned Curats, or learned loyterers in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, without preaching: or with ſuch ſcarcity of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, not above one in a moneth, nay one in a whole yeare, as it was and is in moſt Pariſhes, if not all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey towns of Wales, and too many in England, where atheiſme, profaneneſſe or idolatrous Popery abound. <hi>No one thing</hi> (ſaith B. <hi>White) hath been a greater ſcandall to our</hi>
               <note place="margin">B. White in his Epiſtle to Archbiſhop Lawd in his book of the Sabbath.</note> 
               <hi>Church, then the profane negligence of conformable Miniſters: then their looſneſſe of life, their avarice and ambition in heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together benefices and promotions, and then a groſſe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in diſcharging their duty. On the contrary</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is of greater moment to perſwade the people, then when they ſhall obſerve their Miniſters diligent and induſtrious in ſerving God, and promoting the ſalvation of Chriſtian ſoules committed to their charge.</hi> O ye reformers of the Church, learn this of a Biſhop, and amend this fault, which B. <hi>Laud</hi> would never do.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:48826:5"/>
            <head>The principall Points delivered in this ſhort Apologeticall Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 Concerning the Communion-Table, falſly termed an Altar, what manner of furniture is forbidden, as being ſuperſtitious, where it muſt be placed, and how covered. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>D. Hall</hi> againſt innovations and bravery in Gods worſhip, contrary to the doctrine of Durhamers, <hi>B. Neale</hi> and his Chaplains, <hi>Coſin, Lindſell,</hi> &amp;c. p. 2.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Bernard</hi> againſt the vanity of ſuch which preferre the glory of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Temples before poore-Chriſtians, the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, as Durhamers doe. p. 2.</item>
               <item>4 B. <hi>Motton</hi> out of <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Malachy</hi> againſt ſumptuous orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. p. 3.</item>
               <item>5 The Homilies, and <hi>Hemingius,</hi> concerning true and falſe orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Churches. p. 3.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>Bernard, Auguſtin,</hi> &amp;c. againſt the ſtatelines of Temples, &amp; gawdy ornaments, eſpecially at the Sacraments, which hinder devotion. p. 4.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>Hierome</hi> of the riches; brave furniture, and muſicke in <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, not in ſynagogues nor to be imitated in Chriſtian Churches, into which Pope <hi>Vitalian</hi> was the firſt that brought Organs. p. 5.</item>
               <item>8 <hi>Athanaſius, Conſtantine</hi> the great, <hi>Baſil</hi> of Church-muſicke, and Pſalmes. <hi>Vitalian</hi> hindred preaching with his piping and chancing, as ſome of our Prelates do now. p. 6.</item>
               <item>9 <hi>Juſtine Martyr</hi> and the whole Primitive Church retained the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pſalmes, but they abandoned Pipers and Chanters: and though <hi>David</hi> ordained inſtruments of muſicke for the Temple, yet we may not imitate them no more then we can Aaronicall Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. p. 7.</item>
               <item>10 Our Church ordaineth, that all things be done to edification: but by immoderate muſicke, both Service and Sacraments are worſae underſtood, and turned to theatricall ſtage-playes. p. 8.</item>
               <item>11 Durhamers would not ſuffer the Sacrament of Baptiſme to be miniſtred without an hideous noiſe of Organs and ſingers, with the ſight alſo of many brave images on the Font. But our Homilies teach that we muſt praiſe God that our Churches are quit of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and organs. p. 9.</item>
               <item>12 The Church of <hi>England</hi> termeth Images, Organs, Altars, profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and heatheniſh abominations, yet Durhamers retaine and maintain them ſtoutly. p. 10.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:48826:6"/>
               <item>13 They bow down often and profoundly before their Alter <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Bible, or the body and bloud of Chriſt in the conſecrated Elements, as if the Altar were holler then Chriſts body, and the Bible, yet they ſay they worſhip God, not the Altar: the ſecond Commandement and <hi>B. Buckeridge: each</hi> otherwiſe. p. 10.</item>
               <item>14 B. <hi>Neals</hi> Chaplains, <hi>Coſin, Linſell, James, Duncan, &amp;c.</hi> call bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Altar a comely geſture, and they practiſe it very often, and profoundly, eſpecially at their coming in and going out, is if they would ſalute God, making a low leg before they kneel down to pray: and when they have done prayer, going out of the Church, turn back to look on the Altar, towards which they make another profound leg, taking as it were their leave of God, and departing from God, whom they leave at the Altar. A moſt abſurd foolery. p. 12.</item>
               <item>15 There was never in the world a more abominable idoll then Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Altar. p. 14.</item>
               <item>16 Chriſt upon earth was never ſo worſhipped by bowing down of bodies as Durham Altar hath been. When it was a table ſtanding in the midſt it was as holy as now, yet then it was never bowed unto. p. 15</item>
               <item>17 D. <hi>Coſin</hi> &amp; his fellows which obtruded to the Church ſuch fanatical and idolatrous ornaments, are they not ſeditious innovators? p. 16.</item>
               <item>18 May not the people of Durham be exhorted to communicate in their own Pariſh Churches, as the Law commands them: and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to communicate in the Cathedrall Church, where it is not rightly adminiſtred? yet this is a principall objection against me in their Durham and Yorke Articles and Cenſure. p. 16.</item>
               <item>19 The repreſentation of the death and paſſion of Chriſt is an action of humiliation, of ſorrow and weeping. Why then ſhould our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Prieſts of Durham, pompouſly and gloriouſly attired in ſumptuous Copes imbroidered with images, come to a brave painted Altar with Pipers and Singers, making delicate melody, in ſuch a time of humiliation? p. 18.</item>
               <item>20 Such objects of vanities allure the peoples eyes, eares, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and minds from ſorrowfull meditations of our Saviour Chriſt his death on the croſſe, and our ſinnes which cauſed the ſame: for which we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſufficiently teſtifie our thankefulneſſe, by afflicting our ſelves with mourning and teares. p. 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2 God is angry with us for our ſinnes, which deſerve eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, if he ſhould enter into judgment with us. Therefore we muſt not turne our mourning into merriment, when we would pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cific our angry Iudge. p. 20.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48826:6"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Communion-Table muſt not<note place="margin">The Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table muſt not have ſuperfluous and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but ſuch only as is preſcribed by the Church of England, not ſuch as Biſhop Neal with his Chapleins brought into Durham, and polluted the ſame with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and idolatry.</note> have ſuperfluous and ſuperſtitious ornaments, not allowed by the Book of Common Prayer, Injunctions and Canons, in which whatſoever Ceremony is not bidden, it is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, it is unlawfull it is ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. As the Canoniſts teach, <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitio eſt, relictis Rubricis &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectorio Eccleſiae, alias Ceremonias adhibere pro ſua devotione.</hi> Leaving the Rubricks and direction of the Church, to uſe other ceremonies for devotions ſake, that is ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>The Rubrick and Canon command, that the Communion-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall ſtand in the body of the Church or Chancell, where Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Evening Prayer are appointed to be ſaid: and it muſt ſtand covered with a carpet of ſilk, or other decent ſtuffe, with a faire linnen cloth at the time of the Adminiſtration. And therein Cathedrall and Pariſh Churches muſt be alike, they muſt be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, ſaith the Act of Vniformity.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Table (not Altar) muſt not be removed to the Eaſt end of the Quire or Chancell, as farre as can be from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: It muſt not have a coſtly Velvet cloth with gold fringe and imbroydered with images: much leſſe may it have B. <hi>Neales</hi> precious golden Pall to cover the Altar, having upon it the falſe ſtory of the Aſſumption of our Lady, then which a more abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idoll all Popery cannot ſhew.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt it be a ſumptuous Altar of Stone, gilded, painted and poliſhed bravely, faſtned to the ground, having croſſes, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes, corporaſſes, baſons, tapers, or candleſticks ſet upon it; which by name are forbidden in the 23. Injunction. And never can I find them allowed in any well-reformed Church: ſure I am, they were never in <hi>Durham</hi> Church till Biſhop <hi>Neale</hi> came to that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, 1617.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48826:7"/>
            <p>
               <note n="2" place="margin">B. Halls ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt Innovations and affected bravery in the worſhip of God, and conſequently againſt Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, with their ſumptuous altar, organs, copes, et <hi>caet.</hi>
               </note> It is a dangerous preſumption, ſaith a learned Father of our Church, D. <hi>Hall</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Exceter,</hi> to make innovations, it but in the circumſtances of Gods worſhip.</p>
            <p>These humane additions which would ſeem to grace the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of God, deprave it.</p>
            <p>That infinite Wiſdome knoweth beſt what will pleaſe it ſelfe, and preſcribeth accordingly.</p>
            <p>The fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then the wiſdome of men. Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and falſhood is commonly more gawdy and plauſible the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth. That heart which can for out ward homelineſſe deſpiſe the Ordinance of God, is already alienated from true religion, and lies open to the greateſt ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Never any Prince was ſo fouly idolatrous, as that he wanted a Prieſt to ſecond him. An <hi>Vriah</hi> is fit to humour an <hi>Ahaz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Greatneſſe could never command any thing which ſome ſervile wits were not ready to applaud and juſtifie.</p>
            <p>Thus much ſaith D. <hi>Hall,</hi> whoſe excellent leſſons if the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled innovators and corrupters of our <hi>Durham</hi> Church would have learned and followed, no Sermon need to have been preached againſt ſuperſtitious vanities: with ſuperfluity of which it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly peſtred at this day by our idolatrous altar-building Prieſts, without any direction or approbation of our religious Kings and Princes, who in their Lawes forbid both altars and images, and all other ſuperſtitious rites and ceremonies.</p>
            <p>For they (Biſhop <hi>Neales</hi> Chaplains) have taught the people in their Sermons, that too much coſt cannot be beſtowed upon Chriſt, that is, the Church, and Church-ornaments, brave Altars, rich Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-furniture, gorgeous Veſtments, Sumptuous Organs, glorious glaſſe-windowes, painted, gilded and garniſhed images, and other exceſſive bravery, vaine and unneceſſary, which hath coſt the Church of <hi>Durham</hi> above 2000. pound, wring'd out of poore mens purſes, to the utter undoing of many poore tenants.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="3" place="margin">Bernard cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive vanity of ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adorned Churches, and the neglect of poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghoſt, which is worſe now in Durham, then in the time of Popery.</note> What would <hi>Bernard</hi> ſay, if he were now alive, and ſaw the glory of our Abby-Church (as it is called) the ſuperfluous orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of which have coſt more then would build a faire Church: who thus writeth <hi>AdGul. Abbatem,</hi> to Abbot <hi>William,</hi> making this exclamation: <hi>O vanitas vanitatum, ſed non vanior, quàm inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior: fulget Eceleſia in parietibus, ſed in pauperibus eget.</hi> O vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all vanities, but whether more vaine, or more mad, I know not; the Church ſhineth in trimly decked walls, but in the poore
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48826:7"/> members of Chriſt, it is naked and needy. And who dare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their vaine and mad courſes? who dare gainſay them, or miſlike their doings? if any do ſo, let him look for no better then to be perſecuted to death: for they teach the people, that ſuch are very <hi>Iudaſſes,</hi> Counting all to be waſt, that is beſtowed upon Chriſt; as if Chriſt were in walls, Altars, and Images, more then in the temples of the Holy Ghoſt, the bodies and ſoules of poore Chriſtians: whereby the people learne to contemne their own pariſh-Churches, becauſe they are plaine and ſimple, after the old faſhion, handſome enough and decent, though not ſo proud and ſtately, not brave and magnificent, as this Cathedrall Abby; as now it is adorned paſſing gaily with paintings and gildings.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="4" place="margin">B. Morton out of Ierom upon Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy calleth it a feſtred ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of the Iewes, to eſteeme a brave Altar and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of gold and ſilver better then the godly minds of them that bring oblations.</note> This ſoule errour, and ſuperſtitious folly is thus refuted by D. <hi>Morton</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Lichfield</hi> in his Appeale: If any haply ſhall contemne the worſhip of God becauſe it is not ſumptuous, he ſhall but renew an old infeſtred ſuperſtition of the Iewes, who eſteemed an Altar built of unhewen ſtones, to be but a prophane and polluted thing: As <hi>Ierome</hi> hath obſerved upon the firſt of <hi>Malachy. Reverſus de Babylone populus, Altare tantùm impolitis lapidibus extruxerat;</hi> the people of Iſrael, returning home from the Captivity of Babylon, built an Altar of rough ſtones unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, before there was a Temple, or walls of a City: <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 1. and they eſteemed their religion contemptible, becauſe the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Temple were wanting: to whom God ſpeaketh by the Prophet <hi>Malachy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You thinke that mine Altar is polluted, the ſacrifices alſo laid on the Altar, and the fire that conſumes the ſacrifice you count to be unhallowed and defiled. Neither underſtand ye that Almighty God, regards not, nor lookes for either gold or preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, or a multitude of ſacrifices, but the willing minds of them that bring their oblations.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="5" place="margin">The Church of England in the Booke of Homilies, and Hemin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius ſhew what are true and falſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of Gods Church acceptable to God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to men.</note> Agreeable to this is the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Homilies againſt the perill of Idolatry, and ſuperfluous deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Churches; which utterly diſalloweth our abominable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, Altars and Images, and teacheth wherewith Gods houſe is truely adorned; which are theſe.</p>
            <p>The Word of God ought to be read, taught and heard: the Lords holy name ought to be called upon by publike prayer, and thankſgiving: his holy Sacraments ought duly and reverently to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48826:8"/> be adminiſtred (not gawdily, flauntingly, theatrically) due reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is ſtirred up in the hearts of the godly, by the conſideration of theſe true ornaments of the houſe of God, and not by any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ceremonies, and coſtly and glorious decking of the ſaid houſe or Temple of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pratendunt ornatum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hemingius, ſi illi ornatui adjunctum ſit ullum periculum, ſit maledictus.</hi> They pretend that Altars and Images are ſet up in Churches for ornament, but curſed be ſuch ornaments, to which the perill of Idolatry is joyned.</p>
            <p>And again; <hi>Spiritus Sanctus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ezechiel, Ch. 20. vocat Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la abominationes oculorum, ſed pulvis &amp; cinis ea vocat ornamenta oculorum.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt cals Images and Altars, (all ſuch as God appointed not) the abominations of the eyes, but man that is but duſt and aſhes, cals them ornaments of the eyes.</p>
            <p>And then he concludeth, <hi>Verus ornatus templorum, utilis, &amp; Deo gratus, est concio, cantio, oratio, communio, &amp; non haec quae vel impediunt, vel vitiant:</hi> The true ornaments of Churches, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to men, and acceptable to God, is the preaching of Gods Word, the ſinging of Pſalmes, the adminiſtration of the Sacraments and prayer, and not ſuch things as do hinder and defile the ſame.</p>
            <p>This is the doctrine which the Church of <hi>England</hi> teacheth in ſundry places in the book of Homilies, in the Articles and Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that Images and Altars, ſuperſtitious ceremonies and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous ornaments, piping and ſinging, beautifying of temples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all meane and meaſure, pollute and defile the houſe of God: and none but rotten members of our Church can ſay the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="6" place="margin">Bernard, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, &amp;c. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the too too great magnificence of temples, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cially when they are made theaters, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ears and ey<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodio is tunes, and pompous ſpect<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cles, then oratories to pray and praiſe God, and be edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> alſo reprehended in his time exceſſive heights, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate lengths of Churches, becauſe he miſliked worldly mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence in the ſpirituall ſervice of God, who dwels not in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with hands.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe doth <hi>Auguſtine, Ierome, Iuſtin Martyr</hi> and others, they condemne gay ornaments and pompous ſpectacles of glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pictures, with melodious tunes of pipers, and ſingers in the ſpirituall ſervice of God, eſpecially at the adminiſtration of the holy Communion and Baptiſme; becauſe they hinder godly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations upon our Saviour Chriſt his bitter death and paſſion, and our regeneration repreſented unto us in thoſe myſtical Sacraments. For thus writeth <hi>Bernard</hi> in his Apologie againſt the ſuperfluous ornaments of Churches: I let paſſe the great ſtatelineſſe of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, their immoderate lengths, their vaine breadths, their ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48826:8"/> poliſhings, their curious paintings, which while they draw the ſight of them that pray unto them, they hinder their affection, and they ſeem to me to reſemble the old cuſtome of the Jewes. Mark this, ſaith a learned writer in his Commentary on <hi>Iude,</hi> how <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, that thoſe things which now adayes the defenders of ſuperſtitious vanities, in Popery ſay, were ordained to help de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; as gilded images and coſtly ornaments, curious and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous paintings, and poliſhings of Altars and Temples; they are ſo far from helping, that they hinder devotion, they withdraw, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> not only the ſight of them that pray, but their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction alſo, and they ſmell rather of Judaiſme then Chriſtianiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="7" place="margin">The Iews had but one tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the whole world, and that was beautified with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, altars and veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for the Prieſts to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifices, which could be done no where els, it had ſingers alſo and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But the ſynagogues (which are anſwerable to Churches) where the law of God was read and expounded e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sabbath day, had none of thoſe orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, neither Prieſts, nor prieſtly veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, nor ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, nor muſick, either inſtrumentall or vocall, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould our Church have the like, becauſe they are ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues rather then temples. <hi>Synagoga,</hi> a congregation, an aſſembly.</note> And <hi>Ierome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Nepotian,</hi> concerning the life and converſation of the Clergy, ſaith: <hi>Iewrie</hi> had a rich temple, and all things then made of gold: then thoſe things were allowed of the Lord. Then, that is, they are not now allowed of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And where were they allowed of the Lord? Not in the Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agogues, which the Jewes had in all cities of the countrey, where they aſſembled to heare the Law and the Prophets read and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded every Sabboth day: they had not there either Altars, bloody ſacrifice or incenſe, golden veſſels, or Prieſtly veſtments, muſicall inſtruments or ſingers, but only in the Temple of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, as <hi>David</hi> the King and Prophet, by the inſtinct of Gods Spirit, ordained there to be uſed only when ſolemne ſacrifice was offered. For thus writeth <hi>Arias Montanus: Fuit in templo ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtum, inter ſacerdotes &amp; populum, atrium conſtitutum, in quo Levitae muſicis inſtrumentis ſolennium &amp; quotidianorum ſacrificio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tempore canerent.</hi> There was a pulpit, gallery or ſcaffold ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in a great roome or court betwixt the Prieſts and the people, where the Levites might ſing and play upon their muſicall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when the ſolemne ſacrifices were daily offered. Daily, ſaith he: but <hi>Flavius Ioſephus</hi> the Jew, being himſelf both Prieſt and Levite, knew better what was done: he in his ſeventh book of Antiquities ſaith: <hi>David,</hi> that renowned Prophet of God, deviſed many inſtruments of muſick, and he taught the Levites to ſing and play hymnes to the Lord, <hi>per Sabbathorum dies aliáſque ſol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnitates:</hi> at the ſolemnities of Feſtivall dayes and Sabbaths. Therefore not every day in the week, nor thrice every day: they did not turn the houres of prayer into ſolemne ſervices, with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and chanting, morning, and evening, and mid-day, as our new-fangled ceremony-mongers of late moſt audaciouſly attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48826:9"/> to do in this Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> and did ſo indeed the ſpace of two years without authority, contrary to the Injunctions, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and cuſtomes of our Church, which they were ſworne to obſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vitalianus</hi> himſelfe was not ſo impudently preſumptuous, who was the firſt Pope that brought Organs into Churches, not into his own Chappell at <hi>Rome,</hi> (for there they are not yet, nor ever were, ſaith Cardinall <hi>Cajetan</hi>) not to be uſed but onely upon Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Dayes: and this he did about the yeare of our Lord 660. about 60. years after <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, who would never have allowed ſuch exceſſe of piping and chanting. Of this <hi>Vitalianus</hi> borne at <hi>Signium</hi> a town in <hi>Italy,</hi> thus writeth <hi>Mantuan.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Signius adjunxit, molli conflata metallo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Organa, quae feſtis reſonent ad ſacra diebus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Firſt Pope <hi>Vitalian</hi> to the ſingers joyned his Organs,</l>
               <l>Which might on Holy-Dayes at Service pipe to the people.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <note n="8" place="margin">The ſinging of Pſalm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s commended and practiſed by Ambroſe, Conſtantine the great, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil, and the whole Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church: but organs and prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſong were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in the Church till Pope Vitalian brought them in.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> that great pillar of the Church, which he ſupported againſt Arrianiſme, <hi>Canendi uſum in Eccleſiis interdixit, vanitates fugitans:</hi> In deteſtation of ſuperſtitious vanities, he utterly forbad the uſe of chanting in Churches: but he forbade not the ſinging of Pſalms in a plaine tune, by the whole congregation, which was then allowed, and highly commended by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> and practiſed by the Emperour himſelfe, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſſeth in the fourth Book of the life of <hi>Conſtantine the great: Cantare primus incepit, unà oravit, conciones ſtans reverenter audiit, adeò ut rogatus ut conſideret, reſponderit, fas non eſſe dogmata de Deo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe &amp; ſegniter audire:</hi> This moſt famous Chriſtian Emperour that ever the Church of Chriſt had, he firſt began to ſing the Pſalme, he joyned with the people in prayer to God; ſtanding up reverently, he heard Sermons, inſomuch as being intreated to ſit downe, he anſwered, it is not lawfull to heare the doctrine of God ſlothfully and careleſly.</p>
            <p>So that he uſed not the geſture of ſtanding ſuperſtitiouſly, as a ceremony more holy then ſitting or kneeling, as our upſtart refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers do in this Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> compelling all the people to ſtand, looking about them like fooles and noddies all the time that the <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> is ſung with the Organ, &amp;c. which Creed<note place="margin">Why Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine ſtood to heare.</note> they can neither ſay by heart, nor underſtand one word when it is ſung. But onely that religious Prince ſtood upon his feet, that he might the more attentively heare the Word of God preached.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48826:9"/>
            <p>Neither is it likely the Emperour, on whoſe ſhoulders lay the mannaging of the weighty affaires of ſo mighty an Empire, had leiſure to learn prick-ſong: but in a plaine tune he ſung Pſalmes to God with the whole congregation. Which ſinging of Pſalmes in the vulgar tunes within theſe five yeares (now fifteen yeares) hath<note place="margin">Since the yeare 1627.</note> quite been baniſhed out of <hi>Durham</hi> Church, contrary to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and cuſtome both of this and all other Cathedrall Churches in the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> the Primitive Church alſo, &amp;c. For thus ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi> if the Sea be faire, how is not the congregation aſſembled much more faire, in which a joyned found of men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children (as it were of the waves beating on the ſhore) is ſent forth to God? And the Book of Homilies report out of <hi>Dioniſius,</hi> that hymnes were ſung by the whole multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Adminiſtration of the Communion.</p>
            <p>But Pope <hi>Vitalian</hi> being a skilfull muſician, and a luſty couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous chanter himſelfe, (ſaith a reverend Father of our Church) firſt brought into the Church prick-ſong, deſcant, and all kind of ſweet and pleaſant melody. And becauſe nothing ſhould want to delight the vaine, fooliſh, and idle eares of fond and phantaſticall men and women, he joyned Organs to his curious muſick.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching and <hi>Peters</hi> praying (ſaith he) tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into vaine ſinging and childiſh playing, to the great loſſe of time, and to the utter undoing of Chriſtian mens ſoules, which live not by ſinging and piping, but by every word that comes out of the mouth of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="9" place="margin">The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of the Primitive Church met together to ſing Pſalms, but they had no muſicall inſtruments, ſaith Iuſtin Martyr. Such were left to wanton chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Neither muſt David be imitated in piping and dancing in the Church, which David never did.</note> The Chriſtians of the Primitive Church met together in ſecret caves and corners, for feare of perſecutors, and there they ſung <hi>ante-lucanos hymnos,</hi> as witneſſeth <hi>Pliny,</hi> hymnes to the praiſe of God, in the morning before day, all the people ſung together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any muſicall inſtruments: of which <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſpeaketh in his 170. Queſtion: <hi>Canere eſt pueris conveniens, non ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſed cum inanimis inſtrumentis canere, &amp; cum ſaltatione, &amp; crepitaculis.</hi> To ſing is a thing very agreeable to the nature of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton children, which are not content with ſimple ſinging, but they will pipe alſo and dance, playing with their hands upon timbrels and tabers. But ſaith he, <hi>In Eccleſiis ſublatus eſt ex carminibus, talium inſtrumentorum, &amp; aliorum pueris convenientium, &amp; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt canere ſimpliciter,</hi> i. <hi>ſimplex cantio manet.</hi> Out of the ſongs of Chriſtian Churches the uſe of ſuch inſtruments is quite taken away, and ſuch like childiſh toyes, and there is left onely ſimple ſinging in plaine tunes.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48826:10"/>
            <p>Neither may we imitate the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> in bringing muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inſtruments into our Churches, ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps, lutes trumpets and cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls; for that was a part of the Leviticall ſervice; in the taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and Temple, of which God himſelf was the author, not the idle braine of man. <hi>David</hi> bids that Gods name ſhould be praiſed in the dance, and that praiſes ſhould be ſung unto him on the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bret and harp: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. And in the 68 Pſalme he ſaith: <hi>It is well ſeen (O God how thou goeſt, how thou my God and King goeſt in thy ſanctuary: the ſingers goe before, the minſtrells follow after, in the middeſt are the damoſels playing on the timbrells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may not be ſo abſurd, as (underſtanding literally this myſticall ſong of the Prophet) to bring into this quire, even to the Communion table, or Altar, as they called it, our Sanctuary, or <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> as they make it, minſtrells, and dancers, boyes, and girls playing on timbrells, and tabrets; if we doe, then may we alſo admit to the adminiſtration of the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, inſtead of decent Copes, ridiculous pie-bald veſtments, uſed a long time by the youth of this towne, in their ſports and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>games: which I my ſelf have ſeen with great griefe of heart, and many more beſides mee, have oftentimes ſeene a party<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured fooles-coat (which coſt 3. ſhillings 4. pence, worne even there, at the Communion-table; <hi>Macula indelebilis hujus Eccleſiae, &amp; opprobrium ſempiternum authoribus tantae maculae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> B. Neale, Burgoin, Morecroft,</hi> the firſt introducers of altars, images, tapers, candleſticks, with paultry copes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="10" place="margin">Innovators in Durham have ſo changed ſervices and Sacraments, as if they would have nothing done to edification, contrary to the doctrine of S. Paul and our Church, by incloſing it within railes, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it from the Church and Chancell</note> The book of common Prayer, the Articles of religion, Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Homilies, which containe the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> the denyers and oppugners of which doctrine are not ſound, but rotten members of our Church: thoſe books I ſay, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, and command, all the ſervice to be ſaid and ſung ſo as the people may underſtand all, and be edified therby. But our new fangled reformers of <hi>Durham, Coſin</hi> himſelfe, &amp;c. have within theſe five years brought into this Church ſuch a ſtrange change of Services, nay ſuch a confuſion of the fore-noone Liturgie, that the greater part thereof, can no better be underſtood, then if it were in Hebrew or Iriſh. Nay the Sacrament it ſelfe of the holy Euchariſt, is turned rather into a theatricall ſtage-play, then a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of our Saviour Chriſt his paſſion; At the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which ſo many pictures are exhibited to be ſeene, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceremoniall toyes and Popiſh trinkets, forbidden by the Act
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48826:10"/> of uniformity, and injunctions; And againe, ſo ſtrange, ridiculous, and idolatrous geſtures, with exceſſive noiſe of Muſicall harmony, both inſtrumentall and vocall, at the ſame time, as the like was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſed before, either in this, or any other Cathedrall Church, not onely of England, but of Spaine, Italy, France, and Germany, as travellers report.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="11" place="margin">Not only the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but the Sacrament of Baptiſm alſo hath beene horribly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned, as well with images on the Font, as alſo with immoderate piping and chanting, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrine of our Church in the Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. Blaxton and Coſin.</note> Neither reſt they contented with the horrible prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords Supper, with immoderate chaunting, and Organ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing, and with other ſuperſtitious vanities; but the Sacrament of Baptiſme alſo, they will not ſuffer it to be adminiſtred, without an heideous noiſe of muſick, both of voyces and inſtruments.</p>
            <p>As appeares on Sunday the ſeventh of September 1628. when a child borne in the Colledge was baptized in the Cathedrall Church at Evening prayer, after the ſecond Leſſon as the Rubrick directs.</p>
            <p>In the meane time while one of the Prebendaries baptized the child (which is a principall part of Divine Service) two Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries remaining in the Quire, commanded the Organiſt to play, and the Quire-men, and boyes to ſing the reſt of the Service, at the ſame inſtant that the Sacrament was adminiſtred, with ſuch a noiſe, that they could not heare one another at the Font, to the great offence of many, and of Mr. Deane himſelfe ſtanding at the Font, who grievouſly complained of that inſolent fact of two ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Canons, diſturbing moſt audaciouſly Divine Service, the like to which was never ſeene nor heard in any Church in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</p>
            <p>Such immoderate piping and chanting, with ſetting up of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Altars, have beene even in the beginning of Reformation diſallowed, and baniſhed out of the Church of England.</p>
            <p>For in the ſecond part of the Homily, of the place and time of prayer, we are taught to praiſe God, that our Church is rid of the like piping and chanting, and playing on the Organs (they are the very words of the Homily) that was uſed in Popery, and that our Church is delivered from thoſe things which diſpleaſed God ſo ſore, and filthily defiled his holy houſe, and place of prayer.</p>
            <p>And againe, in the ſame Homily wee read, they have provoked the diſpleaſure and indignation of Almightie God, becauſe they have prophaned and defiled the Churches with Heatheniſh and Jewiſh abuſes, with Images, Idols and Altars, too too ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and intolerably abuſed, with groſſe corrupting the Lords ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48826:11"/> Supper, the bleſſed Sacrament of his body and blood, with an infinite number of toyes, and trifles of their owne deviſing, to make a goodly outward ſhew, and to deface the homely, ſimple, and ſincere Religion of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But now we ought greatly to praiſe God, for that ſuch ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and Idolatrous manners, as were naught, and defaced Gods glory, are utterly aboliſhed, as they deſerved,</p>
            <p>
               <note n="12" place="margin">They that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Homilies, which is the doctrine of our Church, againſt ſuch profanation of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what can they be but the whore of Babylons baſtardly brood? they are no true children of the Church of England.</note> This is the doctrine of our mother the Church of England, in her Booke of Homilies; which whoſoever, borne and bred in the ſame Church, rejecteth, he can be no other then a baſtardly brat of the Whore of Babylon, the Church of Rome, unleſſe he repent, and renounce his foule errors, and returne with teares to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of his gracious Mother, whom he hath moſt ungraciouſly abuſed and offended, by ſetting up Altars and Images, and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sacraments, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For to ſpeake plainly, me thinks theſe words of the Homily, point out in lively colours this our Cathedrall Church of Durham, as now it is changed, from that it was lately in our former Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops time, in which theſe filthy Jewiſh and Heatheniſh abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and intolerable abuſes, which in time of Popery provoked the diſpleaſure and indignation of Almighty God, and prophaned the Lords Supper, the bleſſed Sacrament of his body and blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing long ſince aboliſhed, are now almoſt on a ſuddaine, reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with great advantage.</p>
            <p>As appeareth by the immoderate piping, and chanting at that very time when the Sacraments are adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>By having an exceſſive number of wax candles, whereof ſixty on and about the Altar burning at one time.</p>
            <p>By gilding and painting Images, and Angels, ſet up aloft round about the Quire.</p>
            <p>By erecting a moſt ſumptuous Altar, with brave furniture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto, amongſt which I have ſeene abominable and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Copes, uſed a long time at Maſſe and May games.</p>
            <p>By bowing downe, and worſhipping the ſame Altars, ſo often, and ſo lowly, as never was ſeene the like in the Idolatrous Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="13" place="margin">Bowing to the Altar is an idolatrous Ceremony, brought in and practiſed by B. N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ale and his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, Coſin, Linſell, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goin, corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our Church with ſuperſtitious Innovations.</note> But ſay, they, we worſhip not the Altar, but God; wee bow the knee toward the Altar, not to the Altar, but to Chriſt ſupreame Lord, to whom all religious and divine adoration is due.</p>
            <p>Whoſe death and paſſion are there repreſented at the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48826:11"/> of that Sacrament; Is this true? then are the Papiſts more excuſable, which beleeving the reall preſence, of the true and naturall body of Chriſt, by tranſubſtantiation, they worſhip his body with divine worſhip, and the Altar in reſpect of his body and blood offered thereon in the ſacrifice of the Maſſe.</p>
            <p>But our Altar-worſhippers, never bow the knee to Chriſts body and blood, but to the Altar onely, to the naked Altar, and that continually and daily, whether there bee a Communion or not, turning their backs to the Preacher in the Pulpit, and Miniſters ſaying ſervice, to the whole Congregation alſo, and the Bible it ſelfe, to which they never vouchſafe to make one leg; as if there were more holineſſe in an Altar ſtone, then in the ſacred Scriptures, the Booke of life.</p>
            <p>Theſe their doings are directly againſt the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them; for, either their worſhip is Religious or Civill; if it be Civill, they are abſurd Ideots, in ſhewing more civility to a ſtock or a ſtone, then to a poore man or woman, much better then any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-ſtone, if he be a true Chriſtian, to whom none of them will bow their bodies ſo reverently.</p>
            <p>If it be Religious, they are abominable Idolaters in exhibiting Divine worſhip, due to God alone, to ſuch contemptible creatures, as is an Altar of wood or ſtone.</p>
            <p>Again, either they bow to the Altar in reſpect of God, or to God in reſpect of the Altar, both which reſpects, joyning together God and the Altar, being religious, not civill, make their bowing Idolatrous, and themſelves Altar-worſhippers, (as Biſhop <hi>Buckeridge</hi> Roch. ſaith, <hi>Nec aliud pro illo, nec aliud cum illo:</hi> We may neither adore another thing inſtead of God, nor another thing with God, for he is ſole a God.</p>
            <p>Moreover, every Image when it is worſhipped, is an Idol, and ſeeing the Altar is not truly and properly an Altar, but <hi>ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum,</hi> or <hi>ſimilitudo,</hi> an Image or likeneſſe thereof, therefore the bowing downe of bodies to it, or before it, in regard of ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed holineſſe therein; I ſay that religious, not civill adoration, or proſtration, makes it an Idoll, and they that uſe ſuch comely geſtures (as they call them in their Articles) are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Altar-worſhippers.</p>
            <p>Surely ſuch comely geſtures, neither we, nor our predeceſſours, ſince the reformation of Religion, ever ſaw in this Church; no nor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48826:12"/> the name of an Altar; for the Communion Table was heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us (as you may well remember) till very lately a company of innovators, Biſhop <hi>Neales</hi> Chapleines and favourites began to corrupt and confound our old ſervices, Sacraments, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="14" place="margin">Comely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures to the Altar, not to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ont, or ought els in the Church Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar cringers may as well be termed Altar-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, as the Iſraelites Calf-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers Worſhippers of God make n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t legs to God, but fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down, kneeling, or ſtanding, they lift up their hearts, hands and eyes to heaven, as we are taught to pra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Our father which art in heaven.</hi> When friends p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt one from ano<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, they mutually make legs, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their leave When B. Lawd or D. Coſin go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, turn back to make l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs, do they take their leave of God? do they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from God?</note> They call them comely geſtures, which are indeed Fryar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, moſt ridiculous, and phantaſticall, and (as they are uſed in a principall part of Gods ſervice) they are not onely hiſtrionicall, and mimicall, but impious and Idolatrous.</p>
            <p>Why are not the like comely geſtures uſed at the Altar of the Font, when the Sacrament of Baptiſme is adminiſtred? Is not Baptiſme as comely a Ceremony, becauſe ſo many legs, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, no not one at all is made to the Font; Is not comelineſſe fit for all times and places in the houſe of God? Muſt the Altar at the Eaſt end of the Church be ſo duckt unto, and worſhipped with comely geſtures, and the Weſt-Altar want all comelineſſe of geſtures?</p>
            <p>But it offends them, that they ſhould be called Altar-worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ſo it would have done the Idolatrous Iſraelites, if one had called them Calf-worſhippers; for they profeſſed themſelves to be worſhippers of God which brought them out of the land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, which they knew their golden Calfe did not.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Aaron</hi> built an Altar before it, and made proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying, Tomorrow is a feaſt to the Lord; Then the people ſhouted, and ſang, and danced about the Altar, and the Calfe with great devotion, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and perhaps made low legs and curches, beholding ſo goodly an object, a Calfe of gold whith religious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration; as ſome of us doe to our gay gilded Altar.</p>
            <p>For every man and woman which makes a leg or curchee, they do it to ſome viſible object directly before them; as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Let</hi> did to the Angels that came unto them in the likeneſſe of men, and to the people of the land before whom they bowed themſelves, with civill reverence, as <hi>Iacob</hi> alſo did, when he met his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> hee bowed his body thrice to the ground to appeaſe his wrath.</p>
            <p>But when they, or any elſe did worſhip God, they did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate themſelves upon their faces, or fell downe on their knees, lifting up their hearts, with hands and eyes to heaven, they uſed not to make legs to God above in heaven.</p>
            <p>And this the very Heathen knew by the light of nature, for the Poet ſpeaking of <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> King <hi>Pryamus</hi> his daughter, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48826:12"/> was taken priſoner, at the burning of Troy, writeth thus in 2. Aeneid.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ad coelum tendens ardentia lumina fruſtra,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lumina, nam teneras arcebant vincula palmas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vp to the skies in vaine her eyes <hi>Caſſandra</hi> ſhe lifted,</l>
               <l>Eyes; for palmes of her hands from lifting manacles hindred</l>
            </lg>
            <p>She implored the help of God above, in her diſtreſſe, lookind upward, ſhe made not a low curchie to God in Heaven, whom ſhe ſaw not: ſo it is ſaid of S. <hi>Stephen</hi> in the ſeventh of the <hi>Acts, That he looked up to heaven, and ſaw the glory of God, and Ieſus ſtanding at the right hand of God,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Behold I ſee the heavens open, and the Son of man ſtanding at the right hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It had beene an abſurd thing in <hi>Stephen,</hi> to have made legs to God the Father, and his Son Chriſt, whom he ſaw above his head in heaven; as our leg-makers ſay they doe to God and Chriſt, at the Altar before them.</p>
            <p>For although God be every where, round about us, as well at the Font, in the Weſt end of the Church, as at the Communion Table in the Eaſt: and although heaven be round about the world, yet every man whereſoever he be, even our Antipodes, are taught by the light of nature to apprehend the glorious majeſty of God, to be above his head in heaven.</p>
            <p>There to be worſhipped, with lifting up of heart, hands, and eyes, and not in thoſe parts of heaven which are before, behinde, on the right hand, on the left, or under our feete (as it ſeemeth) on the other ſide of the world. Chriſt teacheth us to ſay, Our Father which art in heaven.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Gentiles which worſhipped viſible Deities in their Images or annexed to them, bowed downe their bodies before the ſame Idols, as that Roman Q. <hi>Catulus</hi> did, of whom <hi>Cicero</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth theſe verſes,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtiteram ſolem exorientem fortè ſalutans,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum ſubito à dextris Roſcius exoritur.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vp as he roſe once ſtood I the Sun with a congy ſaluting,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roſcius</hi> o'th right hand, when I ſpied on a ſudd<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ariſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So that he bowed his knee reverently to the Sun before his face, not above his head, no higher appearing above the Horizon, then the height of <hi>Roſcius</hi> ſtanding on his feet.</p>
            <p>In like manner our Altar-worſhippers, bow their bodies downe to the ground to the Altar ſtanding on the earth, directly before
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48826:13"/> their faces, yet they ſay they make legs to God, and to Chriſt, not to the Altar, then which what can be more abſurd?</p>
            <p>When they have done their prayers upon their knees, then to ſtand up and to make a low leg to God, and going out of the Quire doore, to turne about, and looking on the Altar, make a leg againe to God, taking as it were his leave of God, and farewell, departing from God, as one man doth of another, they take their leaves, bid one another farewell, when they part company, ſhake hands, and mutually make legs.</p>
            <p>To teach the Coriſters going up to the Altar, to make legs to God, when they light the Tapers and when they have done them, to goe backwards with their faces to the Eaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and looking on the Altar, make legs againe to God; at every approaching neere it, and every departing from it, at the taking up or ſetting downe of any thing upon the Altar, ever and anon to make a low curtſie, to make a profound leg to God, eſpecially going out of the Church, as it were taking his leave and departing from God, which is a phraſe of ſpeech, as abſurd as the action it ſelfe is vaine, ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Idolatrous.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="15" place="margin">D Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured and reviled Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people in the Church, yet he made low legs to the Altar, ſo low, that his breech was higher then his head, as vvas proved before the Lords in Parliament.</note> Again, are they not abſurd Ideots, or rather incarnate devils, who in ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Divine Service, will take poore men ſtanding qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly in the Church, and thruſt them out by their heads and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, calling them Pagans; Why ſtand you here you Pagans, if you will not obſerve the Ceremonies of our Church, get you out of the Church.</p>
            <p>Who will ſay to others, even Gentlewomen of the beſt rank, ſitting in their pues; Can ye not ſtand you lazie ſows? taking them by their armes, and tearing their ſleeves to raiſe them up, when the Nicene Creed is ſung; thus Doct. <hi>Coſin</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Who going up to the Altar in a Cope, will ſay in his pride and contempt of poore people, ſtand out of my way ye dirty whor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, diſhonouring the Image of God in them and immediatly make a low leg, downe to the ground, before his Idol the Altar, honouring it, being a ſtock or a ſtone, having unchriſtianly, and uncivilly, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced, and abuſed his Chriſtian brethren &amp; ſiſters at the ſame time.<note place="margin">Durham high Altar the greateſt idoll that ever vvas in the world.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But the holy Altar, ſay they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is not a ſtock or ſtone, neither may it be called an Idoll: Not an Idoll? I doe not thinke that any Idoll in the world was ever ſo worſhipped, as our Durham Altar hath beene.</p>
            <p>Not the Image of <hi>Iupitur Olympius,</hi> or the Philiſtims <hi>Dagon,</hi> or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48826:13"/> the Babilonians <hi>Bell,</hi> or the Trojans <hi>Palladium;</hi> not <hi>Apis</hi> or <hi>Anu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> Oxe or Crocadill, Dog or Cat, <hi>qualia demens Aegyptus portenta colit?</hi> or any other monſtrous Deity of the blinde Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians, that forlorne and miſerable Nation, before the comming of Chriſt, who enlightned them with the knowledge of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, was ever ſo worſhipped, or had ſo much coſt beſtowed on them. When they once fell down on their faces before thoſe Idols, they had done for that time; but every acceſſe, and every regreſſe, and every turning, and every riſing up; and every ſitting, and knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down of the Prieſt and others about the Altar, whether there be a Communion or no, hath a low leg to the Altar.</p>
            <p>Neither are they common curtſies, ordinary legs, ſuch as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and petitioners uſe to make to their Lords and Maſters, but they are wonderfull ſolemne, very profound incurvations, before the venerable Altar, ſo low, that they ſeeme ſometimes to touch the ground with their noſes and beards.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="16" place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion table was never ſo vvorſhipped vvith bovving down before it. And it is a forbidden ceremony both by the Word of God in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and the Church of England. Our Saviour Chriſt living on earth was never ſo vvorſhipped.</note> When it was a Table ſtanding in the midſt of the Quire; it was as good, and as holy as now it is being turned to an Altar, at the Eaſt end of the Church, yet no man or woman, bowed his, or her body to it then, as now they do in a prodigious manner.</p>
            <p>Which ſuperſtitious ceremony of bowing to that Idoll, was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received, and practiſed amongſt us; but within theſe foure or five yeares, by the example, perſwaſion, and compulſion of our new fangled Popiſh Arminians, without any warrant of Gods Word, or direction of the Church, in the Book of Common-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Canons or Injunctions. Nay, it is contrary to the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and forbidden by the Act of Vniformity, and the 12. Canon, and conſequently puniſhable both in the commanders and obeyers.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour Chriſt, when he lived upon earth was bowed unto and worſhipped, by them that acknowledged him to be the Son of God. The Magi Wiſemen of the Eaſt fell on their faces, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him; they did it once, neither they, nor the Shepheards, nor the bleſſed Virgin his Mother, nor <hi>Ioſeph</hi> her husband, danced round about him lying in the cratch or manger, ever and anon making low legs before him, behinde him, on his right hand, on his left, now one after another, now all at once; as daylie is done at our high Altar, in Durham; ſometimes far off, ſometimes cloſe by it, now at the South end, now at the North end, now at the Weſt ſide, ſometimes going forwa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d towards it; ſometimes going backward
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48826:14"/> from it, ſtill nodding their heads, and making legs and curtſies: At which time a delicate noiſe is heard of Organs, Pipers, and Singers, filling the peoples eares with heavenly harmony, as was done when <hi>Nabuchadonozers</hi> golden Image was conſecrated and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="17" place="margin">Our Durham Innovators, Coſin and his fellow<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, which have obtruded to the Church ſuch ſtrange alterations of ſervices and ceremonies, ſet up altars and images, and bow down before them, may they not <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ightly be termed ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony-m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters?</note> They that lately have brought into our Cathedrall Church ſuch fanaticall fopperies, ſuch unlawfull rites and abuſes, whereby it is defiled, the ſervice diſordered, and the Sacraments prophaned, as the Homily teacheth: They that without authority, and againſt authority, even the ſoveraigne authority of our religious Kings and Princes and Parliaments which eſtabliſhed the whole forme of our Liturgy and Ceremonies, in decent and comely manner.</p>
            <p>They that with an high hand, and great violence, durſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly adventure to innovate all things in our Liturgy, to overthwart the well ſetled ſtate of the Church, to put us out of the poſſeſſion of our Religion, and forme of Service which was left unto us by our Anceſtors, and we had quietly poſſeſſed above ſixty yeares.</p>
            <p>They that not onely obſerve themſelves, but compell others to obſerve and approve, their before mentioned ridiculous fooleries, ſuperſtitious vanities, abominations, and Idolatries, contrary to the cuſtome and practiſe of this Church, contrary to the example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cathedrals of this Realme, contrary to Laws, which ſtraitly forbid under great penalties, all Rites and Ceremonies not appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer &amp; Injunctions.</p>
            <p>May not ſuch rightly be termed new-fangled Ceremony-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Idolatrous Altar-worſhippers, ſeditious Innovators, ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall, factious, and turbulent breakers of the peace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of governours? nay rotten members, and rebellious ſons of this our Mother the Church of England, whoſe doctrine and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline they renounce, they corrupt and contemne it, they ſhoulder it out with Popiſh caſhiered antiquities, and outlandiſh Arminian novelties.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="18" place="margin">May not the people be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to communicate in their owne Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where the Sacrament is rightly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, and ſo beare to re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve it in our Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall polluted with idolatry, leaſt we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our own damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Church of England teacheth in the Homilies?</note> Now I pray you, you I ſay, the people of this City have you not Churches at home in your own Pariſhes, not yet polluted with Idols, and Communion-tables not changed into Altars, where you may receive with comfort the holy Communion, in plaine and ſimple manner, as our Saviour ordained, and the primitive Church practiſed, and the Church of England preſcribeth.</p>
            <p>But you muſt needs come hither, and wilfully make your ſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48826:14"/> partakers of our ſins, and ſuperſtitious vanities, when you need not, ſeeing that the holy Sacrament is not rightly adminiſtred in this Chruch of Durham as it was in our former Biſhops time.</p>
            <p>And where it is not lawfully miniſtred, there it cannot ſafely be received without the danger of damnation. Take heed to your ſelves, I warned you before, even this time two yeares, and now I preach to you the ſame doctrine againe, that I may diſcharge mine owne conſcience, and ſave both mine owne ſoule and yours, if you wil heare &amp; obey the voyce of God in this place out of my mouth, as I am charged to ſpeake, and ſo do, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3. 17.</p>
            <p>For thus the Church of England teacheth us in the Homily of the worthy receiving the Communion in the firſt part thereof.</p>
            <p>We muſt addreſſe our ſelves, to frequent the ſame Sacrament, in reverent and comely manner, left as phyſick provided for the body, being miſuſed, more hurteth then profiteth; ſo this comfortable medicine of the ſoule, undecently received, tendeth to our greater harme and ſorrow.</p>
            <p>But above all things, this we muſt be ſure of eſpecially, (ſaith the Homily) that this Supper be in ſuch wiſe miniſtred, as our Lord and Saviour did and commanded to be done, as his holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle uſed it, and the good Fathers of the primitive Church fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented it. For, as that worthy father <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, He is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Lord, that otherwiſe doth celebrate that myſterie, then it was delivered by him, neither can he be devout, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doth preſume to receive it, then it was given by the Author.</p>
            <p>Now who knoweth not what ſtrange alterations have beene brought into this Church, within theſe few yeares, how the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of this Sacrament have preſumed lately to change in many things the adminiſtration thereof, not onely from the practiſe of the primitive Church, and the inſtitution of the author Chriſt; but alſo from the Rubricks, and Canons of the Church, and the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent uſuall cuſtome of this place.</p>
            <p>For it is turned rather into a theatricall Stage-play, where mens eares are filled with pleaſant tunes of muſicall inſtruments, and voyces of not communicating ſingers, and their eyes fed with pompous ſpectacles of glittering pictures, and hiſtrionicall geſtures of men arrayed in maſſing and pibald, not decent robes.</p>
            <p>And other unlawfull, ſuperſtitious and vaine rites, and ridiculous ceremonies are uſed, with which that holy action is defiled and diſgraced: Therefore I did well, and according to my duty and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb facs="tcp:48826:15"/> in admoniſhing that Congregation then aſſembled, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as they were wont to doe, in their owne pariſh Churches, as our Church commandeth, and to forbeare from communicating in this Cathedrall Church, till things were amended, which lately were mar'd; le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t receiving the body and blood of Chriſt, in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely and unlawfull manner, it ſhould tend to their greater harme and ſorrow, as the Homily teacheth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith upon <hi>Pſal. 21. Tempus lugendi eſt, cum paſſio Domini celebratur, tempus gemendi eſt, tempus flendi, tempus confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">19 The celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords ſupper, is the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of his death and paſſion, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by our ſins: therfore it is a time of lamentation and weeping, not of rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, not of pompous and g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ous ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, not of muſick and melody.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; deprecandi;</hi> When the Paſſion of the Lord is celebrated in the holy Communion, by the breaking of his body, which is the bread of life, and powring out his blood, which is the true <hi>aqua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae;</hi> the refreſhing, the comforting, the quickning wine and water of life to languiſhing and dying ſoules.</p>
            <p>That is a time of mourning, a time of ſighing, a time of weeping and lamenting, a time of confeſſing, and begging pardon, it is not a time of piping and ſinging, of wearing and beholding brave cloathes and pictures. And <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, In the preſence of the Lord, teares doe never beg pardon in vaine, and the ſacrifice of a contrite heart never receives repulſe. And againe, he ſaith, in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Lords Supper, and the receiving thereof, As often as I ſee thee ſighing in the preſence of the Lord, I doubt not but the Holy Ghoſt is breathing upon thee: <hi>Cùm intueor flentem, ſentio ignoſcentem,</hi> So often as I ſee thee weeping, I perceive God par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning. And who comes to crave pardon of an angry King, and terrible Judge, whom he grievouſly offended, with many haynons crimes deſerving death, who, I ſay, dare come into his preſence, <hi>Pompaticè, &amp; glori<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> pompouſly and gloriouſly, in ſlanting apparell, in goodly Babyloniſh robes, imbroidered with Images of ſilver, gold and pearle, and with an excellent conſort of Muſitians ſinging merrily, piping and playing joyfully and jollily.</p>
            <p>And D. <hi>Buckeridge</hi> the late Biſhop of Rocheſter, now of Ely, ſaith very well, in his Book of kneeling at the Communion; What hath muſick to do with mourning? or a ſong of mirth, with a day of the greateſt ſorrow, which is the Paſſion of Chriſt, when the ſeeds of contrition and repentance muſt be ſowed with teares, that the harveſt in Heaven may be reaped with joy.</p>
            <p>And againe, we muſt come weeping before him, that offered up ſupplications, and prayers, with ſtrong cries and teares to redeeme us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 7. Wee muſt proſtrate our ſelves humbly before our
<pb facs="tcp:48826:15"/> Judge that is offended by us, and weepe before him whom wee would pacifie with our teares and compunction; So then, ſaith he, ſince we come to the Lords houſe, and table to pacifie him, let our caraiage be ſuch, that we ſtir him not to more anger; we muſt ſhut up our ſenſes that they wander not; our eyes muſt ſee Gods beauty, not gad after vanities, and ſend teares as Embaſſadors: Our eares muſt attend the word of truth, not delicious tunes of muſicall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="20" place="margin">Such gaudy ornaments and paultry furniture as are uſed in Du<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ham Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans &amp; other muſick, hinder godly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore K. Iames when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Communion at Durham on Eaſter Day 1617. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all things to be done plainly without mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick or other bravery.</note> Why then are ſet before us ſo many objects of vanity, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny allurements of our outward ſenſes, our eyes &amp; eares, &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our minds from the meditation of Chriſts death &amp; paſſion, and our ſins which were the only cauſe of all our miſeries, &amp; his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable ſufferings. Can ſuch paltry toyes bring to our memory Chriſt and his blood-ſhedding? Croſſes, Crucifixes, Tapers, Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, gilded Angels, painted Images, golden Copes, gorgious Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, ſumptuous Organs, with Sackbuts and Cornets piping ſo loud at the Communion table, that they may be heard halfe a mile from the Church? <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, no. <hi>Orantium in ſe retorquent aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, impediunt affectum:</hi> Such glorious ſpectacles, draw away from God the minds of them that pray, they further not, but hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der entire affections, and godly meditations.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of which impediments of devotion, moved our moſt learned and religious King <hi>Iames,</hi> when he received the holy Communion in this Cathedrall Church, upon Eaſter-day, 1617. to give charge, or at leaſt in his name charge was given (upon my knowledge I ſpeake it, and in my hearing, in mine own houſe) that the Communion ſhould be adminiſtred in plain ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; &amp; it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commanded, that no chaunting ſhould be uſed by the Quire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor playing on the Organs or other Inſtruments: Which my ſelfe being treaſurer of this Church at that time, and receiving the Communion with his Majeſty (as my office required) I did ſee, &amp; take order, ſhould be performed, according to the Kings pleaſure &amp; direction; at which time there were no Images, or other gay and gaudy monuments of ſuperſtition and Idolatry to be ſeene.</p>
            <p>Two Copes indeed were worne, both decent, as the Canons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, not party-coloured nor pibald, like ours at Durham, but plaine without any picture, or other imbroidring of Croſſes, or Images, which the doctrine of the Church of England, in the book of Homilies, and Injunctions, ſtraightly forbids in our Churches to be uſed at any part of Gods ſervice, eſpecially at the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:48826:16"/> table, or in windowes ab<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſhall we <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffect ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and extraordinary bravery, ſuch a deale and ſo great variety of delicious muſick at the receiving of the holy Communion, an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the greateſt humiliation and mourning, which the religiou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſedome of ſo learned a Prince forbad, and refuſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="21" place="margin">When we come to Gods <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we muſt endeavour to pacifie his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with our humiliation and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not provoke him againſt us with our proud beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and flaunting! bravery.</note> When: we come to Gods houſe, and ſacred table to pacifie him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (ſaith the Biſhop of Rocheſter, in his Book of kneeling at the Communion, <hi>pag.</hi> 19.) our carriage muſt be ſuch, that we ſtir him not to more anger; and how can lie but be angry, when we turne our mourning into merriment, our faſting and prayer into ſtage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing, ſaith he? And again, in the ſame book, we muſt weep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, to waſh away our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins, and deplore and prevent our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future miſery: The depth of ſin; ſaith he, pierced not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his hands and feet, but his heart alſo; in which he offered up prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong cryes and teares, that he might overcome the clamour of our crying ſins.</p>
            <p>And if our Saviour wept for us, the Redeemer for the redeemed, we have much more reaſon to weepe for our ſelves, and let none be found ſo prophane amongſt us, that when the ſon of God wept and ſuffered for our redemption, we ſhould laugh, and make merry, pipe and ſing at our condemnation, as if we were ſenſeleſſe of our owne confuſion. We may not preſume to eate the bread of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and forget the duty of ſinfull, and earthly men that are but duſt and aſhes.</p>
            <p>Reverend and dreadfull myſteries muſt have receivers that come with reverence and dread; and ſuch as our action is, ſuch muſt be our affection, that is, to receive that with feare and trembling, (and not with piping and ſinging) which is ſo fearefull and dreadfull in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And then he concludeth, with this admonition; Behold thou ſinner how great reproaches Chriſt ſuffers at thy hands, who by thy wilfull impieties, doeſt crucifie againe to thy ſelfe the Lord of life.</p>
            <p>And then reſolve, that as Chriſts hands, and feet, and head, and every poare and paſſage of his body, was a fountaine of mercy that runs in his blood: ſo thine heart muſt be as a ſpring of ſighs and groanes, and thine eyes muſt be as fountaines of teares, to waſh with <hi>Magdalen,</hi> not ſo much Chriſts feet, as thine owne ſoule.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48826:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
